Imagine
you're trying to divide a massive just
sprawling network into two distinct
groups. Um, this could be, you know, a
city's power grid, a complex social
network,
>> or well, even the microscopic wiring
inside the device you're listening to
right now.
>> Yeah, exactly. But your goal here isn't
to just isolate these two groups. Your
goal is to actually maximize the
connections that cross that dividing
line,
>> which I mean, it sounds totally
counterintuitive. Usually when we
fracture a system, we want a clean
break, like minimal entanglement.
>> But think of it like um hosting a
massive dinner party. You have to split
your friends into two separate tables
because of space, but you want the party
to be lively, right? Chaotic even.
>> Oh, I see where you're going with this.
>> Yeah. So, you want to maximize the
number of close friends sitting at
opposite tables. You're forcing them to
like shout across the room and mingle
between the two groups. You want the
highest possible weight of connections
crossing the gap.
>> That is wow. That's a brilliant way to
visualize the core tension of the
manuski problem. I love that. It's
really the mathematical art of finding
the optimal fracture point in a system
um just to maximize tension across that
fracture.
>> And that tension is basically the
central mission for our deep dive. Today
we are exploring a super fascinating
2026 presentation by a researcher named
Lux036.
It's titled Hadlock's algorithm for
planer maxity and MWPM optimization.
>> Quite a mouthful.
>> It is. Yeah, but we're going to unpack
this brilliant mathematical breakthrough
from 1975 that took a famously
impossible problem and found a cheat
code to solve it. And then we'll get
into a modern optimization that takes
this 1975 logic and makes it run at like
absolute lightning speed.
>> Well, to really appreciate the elegance
of this cheat code, we first kind of
need to understand the nightmare that
this problem presents in the wild. You
know,
>> the impossible part.
>> Exactly. If you have a general graph,
just a random messy web of nodes and
connections with no specific structure,
mech is basically unsolvable in a
reasonable time frame. It falls into a
category computer scientists call np
hard.
>> Right? And let's translate that for a
second. NP hard basically means the
complexity scales so aggressively that
as you add more nodes to your network,
the number of possible ways to split the
group just explodes factorially.
>> Oh, it's brutal. If you tried to brute
force a solution for a network of any
real size, I mean, even a supercomput
would be crunching numbers until the
heat death of the universe.
>> Yeah, literally. For decades, handing a
mathematician a general graph and asking
for the absolute maximum cut was well a
guaranteed way to get laughed out of the
room,
>> right? Because you just couldn't do it.
>> You couldn't. Historically, the best we
could do was rely on incredibly heavy
geometry to find approximations. M
>> um the famous one is the Goldman's
Williamson STP algorithm.
>> Okay. But that's just a guess, right?
>> Yeah, exactly. You don't get the perfect
optimal answer. You just get a
mathematically good enough guess. I
mean, the only time it was easy was if
your graph happened to be perfectly
bipartite,
>> meaning it naturally splits into two
neat groups already,
>> right? Where all connections already
cross the divide. In that rare case, the
problem is trivial. You literally just
cut down the middle.
>> But, you know, the real world is messy.
Most networks aren't perfectly
bipartite, which brings us to the
specific arena where Hadllock's 1975
algorithm operates, which is planer
graphs.
>> Yes, this is where the impossible
suddenly becomes possible.
>> So, let's define that. A planer graph is
a network with a very strict geometric
rule. You must be able to draw it on a
flat piece of paper or the surface of a
sphere without any of the connecting
lines, the edges crossing over each
other.
>> Like a map with no overpasses. Every
single intersection has to be an actual
node, a physical location in the
network.
>> And mathematics is pretty ruthless about
enforcing this, right?
>> Oh, absolutely ruthless. To be
considered planer, a graph strictly
excludes certain inherent structures.
For instance, if your network contains a
fully connected group of five nodes,
what mathematicians call K5, it's game
over
>> because you can't draw it
>> right. There is simply no physical way
to draw five nodes all connected to each
other on a flat plane without at least
two lines crossing. It also excludes a
structure called a complete bipartite
3x3 graph or K33.
>> So if either of those shapes is hiding
inside your sprawling network,
>> it's not planer.
>> Yeah. But if your network passes that
test, a really fascinating geometric
property emerges. The drawing of the
network divides the blank paper into
distinct enclosed regions. We call these
empty spaces faces.
>> Okay, wait. I have to push back on this
definition of faces because looking
through the source material, something
felt like a total mathematical cheat to
me.
>> Oh, how so?
>> Well, I totally understand faces when
they are enclosed, right? Like if I draw
a triangle on a piece of paper, the
empty space inside that triangle is a
face. It's clearly bounded by the three
lines,
>> right? Makes sense.
>> But the math dictates that the empty
space outside the triangle, the blank
paper stretching out to infinity in
every direction is technically
considered a single face with a
boundary. I mean, how can infinity be a
bounded region?
>> Uh, yeah, it does feel like a cheat when
you restrict your mind to a flat
two-dimensional piece of paper, but
remember the full definition we just
talked about,
>> the sphere thing.
>> Exactly. A planer graph can be drawn on
a plane or the surface of a sphere. So
imagine taking that flat piece of paper
with your triangle drawn on it and
wrapping it perfectly around a globe.
>> Oh wow. Okay, I see it now.
>> Right. The infinite outer space wraps
around the back of the sphere and closes
in on itself. On a spherical surface,
the so-called outer face is just another
bounded region on the globe. It's
completely democratized.
>> That is wild.
>> Yeah. Mathematically, it's identical to
the space inside the triangle. Infinity
just disappears.
>> Wrapping it around a sphere democratizes
the faces. The inside and the outside
are just two different patches on a
ball. I really love that perspective
shift.
>> It's beautiful, isn't it?
>> So, okay, we have our planer graph and
we know it's composed of these faces,
these empty spaces. How did Hadlock look
at empty space and somehow use it to
solve an NP hard problem?
>> Well, he shifted his entire focus from
the nodes to the boundaries. He
categorized every single face in the
network into one of two camps. Even or
odd.
>> And this is based on what? based purely
on the number of edges that form the
boundary of that specific face. So a
square is bounded by four edges making
it an even face. A triangle is bounded
by three making it an odd face.
>> And this seemingly simple distinction, I
mean this is where the entire maxiut
problem breaks wide open, right?
>> Literally does
>> because our goal is to divide all the
nodes into two sets. Let's call them set
A and set B. If a face has an even
number of edges on its boundary, like a
square, you can perfectly alternate the
nodes as you walk around the perimeter.
Set A, set B, set A, set B.
>> Exactly. Every single edge around that
square will successfully cross from A to
B.
>> Right. You can perfectly two-color it.
Every edge is included in your cut and
the face is completely satisfied.
>> But try applying that exact same
alternating logic to an odd face like a
triangle.
>> You just can't. Node one is set A. Node
two is set B. Node three goes back to
set A. But now node three and node one
are right next to each other and they're
both in set A.
>> Yep. The edge between them does not
cross the divide.
>> It's trapped entirely inside set A.
Mathematically, it is literally
impossible to perfectly twocolor an odd
face. At least one edge on its boundary
has to be excluded from your cut.
>> So odd faces are fundamentally
frustrated. And that's actually the term
used in physics and graph theory to
describe this state. Frustrated. There's
no perfect resolution for them. Someone
is always left out.
>> It's like a threeperson love triangle.
Two people can pair off perfectly, but
someone is always left out in the cold.
>> That's a perfect analogy. And there's
this beautiful ironclad rule in planer
graph theory called the handshaking
lema. It proves that every planer graph,
no matter how complex, will always
contain an even number of these
frustrated odd faces.
>> So, they always exist in pairs.
>> Always. If you're listening to this and
wondering why chip manufacturers or data
scientists care about frustrated odd
faces, this is the light bulb moment
right here.
>> Oh, for sure.
>> If the even faces are perfectly happy
and easily divided and the odd faces are
the sole source of the frustration, then
finding the maximum cut isn't about
looking at millions of individual nodes
anymore.
>> Not at all.
>> It just becomes a highly targeted game
of dealing with the odd faces.
>> Exactly. Hadlock realized that to solve
max skate on a planer graph, you just
need to identify these frustrated odd
faces, right,
>> and calculate the absolute cheapest way
to pair them up and resolve their
frustration.
>> Let's walk through how the algorithm
actually does this step by step because
it's a really fascinating sequence of
logical leaps. The first thing the
computer does is verify the graph is
actually planer. Right.
>> Right. Using a standard library tool
like Python's annex. Planerity. This
maps out the embedding so it gives the
computer the exact geometric layout of
the boundaries.
>> But the next move is where the genius
really lies. The algorithm constructs
what is called a dual graph.
>> Yeah, the dual graph is a complete
inversion of perspective. You take every
face from your original graph, the empty
spaces themselves,
>> and you turn them into the new vertices.
And the new edges that connect these
faces are the physical boundaries they
share in the original graph. And if two
faces happen to share multiple
boundaries, the algorithm is smart
enough to only keep the one with the
lowest weight.
>> It's kind of like looking at a map of
countries. In the original graph, the
cities are the nodes and the highways
between them are the edges.
>> Okay, I like that.
>> But in the dual graph, the countries
themselves become the nodes, and the
physical borders between them become the
connecting edges. The weight of that
border is just the weight of the highway
crossing it.
>> That is spot on. Once you have that map
of countries, you filter it down. You
basically isolate the troublemakers by
stripping away all the even faces,
leaving only the odd ones,
>> the frustrated ones,
>> right? Then the algorithm calculates the
all pair shortest paths. It explores the
dual graph to find the absolute cheapest
route across the borders to connect any
odd face to any other odd face.
>> And because the handshaking lema
guarantees there's an even number of
them, we know they can all eventually be
paired off.
>> Exactly. Which leads us to a process
called minimum weight perfect matching
or MWPM.
>> Right?
>> We take this matrix of shortest paths
and calculate the optimal way to pair up
every single odd face so that the total
distance the combined weight of all the
paths is as tiny as mathematically
possible.
>> So we are finding the lowest possible
cost to resolve all the frustration in
the whole network.
>> Yes. Then comes the final crucial
maneuver. We trace those optimal
shortest paths in the dual graph back to
the original highways, the primal edges
in our network. And the edges that make
up those paths are explicitly removed.
>> They're the edges we exclude from our
cut.
>> You got it. The remaining edges form a
bipartite subgraph, which is our MXCUT.
>> I just want to pause and highlight the
sheer irony of this logic for a second.
We are running this deeply complex,
highly sophisticated algorithm to find
the absolute minimum total weight
>> so we can throw it away.
>> Exactly. We are systematically hunting
for the cheapest trash to take out
because mathematically throwing away the
minimum guarantees that the pile of
connections we are left holding is the
absolute maximum.
>> It is a stunning bit of reverse
engineering. Let's ground this with the
simple triangle example from the
presentation. It's a network with just
three nodes and three edges. And let's
say the edges have weights of 5, 10, and
three.
>> Okay, a triangle that means it has two
faces. The inner face bounded by the
three edges,
>> right? And the outer face, the rest of
the world, which we now know wraps
around our imaginary sphere and is also
bounded by those same three edges. So
both faces are odd.
>> Both are odd. Both are frustrated. To
pair them up and resolve the
frustration, you have to cross from the
inside to the outside,
>> which means crossing one of the edges,
>> right? You can pay a cost of five, cost
of 10, or a cost of three.
>> The shortest path algorithm immediately
identifies the edge weighing three.
>> So we exclude the three. We literally
throw it in the trash and we are left
with the edges weighing 5 and 10. 5 + 10
is 15. That's our maximum cut.
>> You've just executed Hadlock's algorithm
in your head. It is mathematically
foolproof,
>> which is amazing. But you know, if this
logic was perfected in 1975, it raises
the obvious question of why Lux 036 is
doing a whole presentation on it in
2026.
>> Ah, yes, the answer there is the
relentless scale of modern technology.
When engineers take Hadlock's elegant
mass and try to feed it a modern circuit
netlist like the blueprint of a
microchip containing millions of
microscopic wires,
>> it crashes.
>> The algorithm hits a terrifying
computational wall. The calculation just
gets way too heavy.
>> Too heavy. How?
>> Specifically, the bottleneck is
calculating those all pairs shortest
paths on the dual graph. The time it
takes to compute that scales cubically.
In computer science terminology, it has
a time complexity of big O of V duel
cubed.
>> Oof. Let's unpack what cubic scaling
actually means for a processor because
it is brutal. It basically means if your
network gets 10 times larger, the mass
doesn't take 10 times longer to solve.
It takes 10 times 10 x 10.
>> Takes a thousand times longer.
>> Exactly. So for a modern circuit net
list with thousands or even millions of
faces, the processing time stretches
from like seconds into literally months.
>> And that is the exact problem the 2026
presentation solves. The solution is an
optimization called bconnected component
decomposition or BC decomposition. The
researchers leveraged a hidden
structural property of the angu problem
on planer graphs which is that the
results are additive over boned
components.
>> We probably need to define what a boned
component looks like for everyone.
>> Sure. Imagine a sprawling network that
has a structural bottleneck. Yeah.
>> So, two large dense clusters of nodes
that are connected to each other by only
one single node in the very middle. That
single critical connecting node is
called an articulation point.
>> Right?
>> If you were to delete that one node, the
entire graph would split into two
completely disconnected pieces.
>> It's an hourglass shape. Essentially,
the articulation point is the pinch in
the middle where the sand falls through.
>> Exactly. So a bonconnected component is
a solid block of the network that
contains absolutely no articulation
points inside it. You'd have to
aggressively remove at least two or more
nodes to break it apart.
>> Okay, so how does that help us?
>> The breakthrough insight here is all
about cycles. Because these separate
components only touch each other at that
single articulation point, they can
never ever share any edges. It is
physically impossible for a cycle to
loop through one block, cross the pinch
point, travel through the second block,
and somehow circle back without crossing
that pinch point a second time.
>> And since MX Soet is ultimately about
breaking cycles to resolve those
frustrated faces, the fact that no
cycles overlap means the math in one
block has absolutely zero impact on the
math in the other blocks.
>> Exactly. You can completely sever the
graph at those articulation points. You
just hand each block to the processor to
solve entirely independently and then
you union the final results together at
the very end.
>> Okay, let me try an analogy here. It's
like trying to perfectly divide a giant
really intricate solid chocolate bar. If
you try to snap the whole massive thing
in half all at once, the force will
probably shatter it into a chaotic mess,
>> right? Total disaster.
>> But if that chocolate bar has those deep
grooves pressed into it, those are our
articulation points. You don't try to
snap the whole thing. You easily break
it down along the grooves into
bite-sized squares. You divide those
tiny squares effortlessly. And when you
push the divided piles back together,
you get the exact same perfectly split
result, but you used a fraction of the
energy.
>> That analogy perfectly captures the
mechanics. Yeah. By conceptually
breaking the graph apart at the
articulation points, we aren't changing
the final maximum cut at all, but we are
fundamentally altering the geometry of
the processing time. Let's actually talk
about the math of that processing time
because it's nuts. When you're dealing
with a problem that scales cubically,
breaking the input data down doesn't
just save a little bit of time. It
causes a massive collapse in
computational weight.
>> It really does.
>> If you find just one articulation point
right in the middle, splitting your
network into two equal blocks, the math
changes from nub to calcula
resolves to nub / 4. You get an
immediate 400% performance boost just
for slicing the problem in half once.
And obviously the more components you
break it into the more extreme the speed
up becomes.
>> So how do they physically find those
pinch points in the code?
>> Modern software utilizes Taran's bridge
finding technique which relies on a
depth first search. It's actually a
really fascinating mechanism. The
algorithm essentially drops a digital
breadcrumb trail
>> like Hansel and Gretle.
>> Exactly. It relentlessly walks a path
deep into the network until it gets
stuck. If it explores a whole cluster of
nodes and realizes the only possible way
back to the start is to walk backward
along the exact same path it just came
down, it knows that connection is a
bridge
>> and the node connecting it is an
articulation point,
>> right? So it rapidly crawls the graph
and collects these independent node
sets.
>> But you know the speed up for the
shortest paths calculation is only half
the victory here, right? The
decomposition also completely transforms
how we handle step five, the MWPM, where
we calculate the perfect matching of the
odd faces.
>> Yes, because the matching step is also
fundamentally cubic in complexity. But
because we've shattered the graph into
these tiny bite-sized boned components,
the number of frustrated odd faces
trapped inside any single block drops
dramatically
>> just structurally.
>> Exactly. The researchers documented that
after applying BCD decomposition, the
vast majority of blocks end up
containing 18 or fewer odd faces.
>> Okay, why is the number 18 so critical
here?
>> Well, it comes down to that factorial
explosion of combinations we mentioned
earlier. If a block had say 100 odd
faces, the number of possible ways to
pair them up is so astronomically large
that you'd have to use a greedy
approximation. And a greedy algorithm
just looks at the data and says, "What
is the absolute cheapest pairing right
next to me in this exact moment?"
>> Right? It takes the immediate cheapest
option. But that short-sighted decision
might force a terribly expensive pairing
later on. You lose precision. But 18
faces that that is a small enough
combination space that a standard modern
processor can hold the entire matrix in
its memory at once.
>> It basically drops below the threshold
where approximations are even necessary.
>> Precisely. So instead of a greedy guess,
developers can deploy an exact dynamic
programming approach.
>> Okay. Dynamic programming.
>> Yeah. Which maps out overlapping
subpros. It explores the combinations
perfectly to find the absolute optimal
overall setup rather than just taking
what looks good in the moment.
>> The decomposition doesn't just make the
algorithm exponentially faster. It
ensures the MWPM step is mathematically
perfect.
>> Speed and absolute precision. I mean,
that's the holy grail of optimization
right there. And the source material
makes it clear that this isn't just a
theoretical white paper either. They
highlight actual code implementations
built for production.
>> Yeah, they really brought this to life.
>> There is a Python package called Netlist
X that handles this BC optimized logic
and for raw industrial-grade
performance. They built Netlist X CPP in
C++.
>> And honestly, the C++ implementation is
a masterclass in modern software
engineering. It specifically leverages
C++ 20 cor routines to perform what's
called lazy iteration.
>> Let's translate lazy iteration for a
sec. It essentially means the computer
acts like a highly efficient
procrastinator.
>> I love that. Yeah.
>> Instead of aggressively calculating and
storing the entire massive map of data
in its memory all at once. A co- routine
pauses. It only calculates the exact
piece of data the algorithm needs at the
precise millisecond it's asked for it.
It's like a chef who refuses to chop all
the vegetables in the morning, but waits
until the very moment a customer orders
a salad.
>> Exactly. It saves massive amounts of
memory overhead.
>> And they also manage the build process
using XMake, which is a modern,
incredibly fast build utility that
replaces older systems like CMake. It
just points to a highly streamlined
contemporary development pipeline.
>> Okay, this all sounds like absolute
magic. I mean, we took a 1975
mathematical cheat code, dusted it off,
supercharged it with bconed component
chunking, and ran it on ultramodern C++
core routines.
>> It's quite the journey.
>> It is, but I have to play devil's
advocate for a second. Is there a catch?
Like, are there scenarios where a data
scientist should look at their network
and decide not to use this
decomposition?
>> It's a vital question because yeah, this
optimization is wildly powerful, but it
is highly dependent on the physical
shape of your data. BCD decomposition is
a lifesaver for sparse circuit net
lists, sprawling gridlike structures, or
hierarchical designs.
>> Basically, things that look like chaotic
spiderwebs with lots of natural pinch
points,
>> the chocolate bars with lots of deep
grooves, right?
>> But it offers absolutely zero benefit if
your graph doesn't possess those pinch
points. If you're analyzing a highly
dense planer graph or a tightly woven
triangulated mesh, it might be one giant
solid bonic component. Ah, so if you run
the Targent search on that,
>> the algorithm will crawl the entire
structure, realize there are no
articulation points, and you will have
wasted processing power only to end up
right back at the original cubic
bottleneck.
>> Ouch.
>> Yeah. It's also completely unnecessary
for very small networks, say under 50
nodes. At that scale, the administrative
overhead of actually splitting the graph
takes longer than just solving it
outright. Knowledge is most powerful
when you understand the boundaries of
its application. Use the right tool for
the exact shape of the problem. Makes
perfect sense. So what does this all
mean when we pull back and look at the
big picture? We started with a famously
intractable NP hard problem trying to
cleanly divide a complex network while
maximizing the tension across the gap.
>> Right? We learned that if the network
can be drawn flat on a piece of paper, a
brilliant mathematician in 1975 found a
workaround. By ignoring the nodes and
looking exclusively at the empty spaces,
the faces, he realized the odd shapes
were mathematically frustrated.
>> And by running an algorithm to find the
absolute cheapest way to remove that
frustration, he threw away the
mathematical minimum, ensuring he was
left holding the absolute maximum. And
then we jump to 2026 to see how
engineers forced that elegant solution
to survive the crushing scale of modern
microchips. By utilizing depth first
search to identify articulation points,
we can fracture an impossibly heavy
calculation into tiny independent
lightning fast blocks.
>> Switching to exact dynamic programming
to get a flawless result in a fraction
of the time. If you're listening to this
and facing an overwhelming, seemingly
impossible project in your own life or
career, I think the takeaway here is
really profound. The answer isn't always
to brute force the whole massive problem
at once.
>> No, rarely is.
>> Look for the underlying geometry of your
challenge. Are there natural
articulation points? Can you find the
pinch points where you can break a
massive, intimidating undertaking into
independent, manageable blocks that you
can solve perfectly on their own? It
completely reframes how you approach
complexity, doesn't it? You don't have
to swallow the problem whole.
>> You really don't. And it leaves me with
one final lingering thought to explore
today. Hadlock solved an impossible
problem, not with brute force, but with
a total shift in perspective. He didn't
look at the tangible objects. He didn't
look at the nodes. And he didn't look at
the connections. He found the perfect
answer by deeply analyzing the empty
space between them. So, what other
intractable problems in science, in
business, or even in our own personal
lives might suddenly become perfectly
solvable if we just stopped staring so
hard at the objects themselves and
started analyzing the empty space?
>> That is a phenomenal question to ponder.
>> Something to mull over until next time.